# MOHAMMAD JASIM USMANI

**८**+1(514)-516-1273 ★ Montreal, QC H4G 2A9, Canada (**Open to Relocate anywhere in Canada**)

#### **SUMMARY**

**Data Scientist/Engineer** with a Master's degree and 2+ years of experience in data ingestion, cleaning, analysis, and visualization using **Python, SQL and data science libraries**. Adept at **raw data exploration** and turning domain knowledge into insights. Excellent communicator with a passion for **data quality**, self-motivated, and quick learner in fast-paced settings.

#### TECHNICAL EXPERTISE

• Language: Python, C++, SQL, MATLAB

• Data Analysis tools: MS Excel, Power BI

• Database: PostgreSQL, MySQL

- Development Tools: Git, Github, GitLab, Microsoft Visual Studio, PyCharm, Jupyter, Slurm, Jira, Confluence
- Big Data Framework: Snowflake, Matillion, Apache Spark Ecosystem (Spark SQL, Spark Core, Spark ML-lib)
- **Deep Learning Frameworks & Library:** TensorFlow, PyTorch, NumPy, Scikit-learn, Pandas, Matplotlib, Keras, XGBoost, SciPy, Seaborn, OpenCV, Langchain.
- Data Visualisation Tools: Matplotlib, Seaborn, plotly, ggplot, Streamlit

#### **EDUCATION**

 Master of Applied Science, ECE, Specialization in Machine Learning Concordia University 2021 - 2023 Montreal, QC, Canada

Relevant Coursework: COMP 6321 Machine Learning (Grade: A+),

COEN 6331 Neural Networks (Grade: A-)

Awarded 33,000 CAD stipend scholarship

• Bachelors in Electrical Engineering, Specialization in Soft Computing Jamia Millia Islamia University, India

2016 - 2020 New Delhi, India

#### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

# • Data Scientist/Engineer

Precision Medicine Group

February 2024 -Montreal, QC, Canada

- Collaborated in building end-to-end ETL pipelines using AWS, Snowflake, and Matillion for ingesting data from APIs in type 2 SCD tables.
- Collaborated with cross-functional teams to ingest data and develop a streamlit app for holiday calendar
  for employees world wide, resulting in a 30% reduction in scheduling conflict.
- **Assisting** in developing and maintaining vector database for various AI applications.
- Applied advanced analytics and machine learning techniques to solve business problems, delivering data-driven solutions in recommendation systems for sales team.

# Machine Learning Engineer / Researcher Aerospace Robotics Lab, Concordia University

Jan 2022 - Dec 2023 Montreal, QC, Canada

Project: Accelerating Graph Neural Networks for Real Time Physics Simulation

- Developed a novel algorithm and framework for training AI model using **Graph neural network** to predict rovers or vehicles escape when stuck in sand in real-time.
- Implemented the rigid body correction for graph neural network prediction during inference which led to an accuracy of **92.7** % to generate visualisations using matplotlib.

- Accelerated the runtime of the model by 3x (from **0.34 seconds** per frame to **0.12 seconds**) while retaining the accuracy.

## • Machine Learning Developer CRIM (Computer Research Institute of Montreal)

Jan 2023 - April 2023 Montreal, QC, Canada

#### Project: Object Detection in satellite images using Diffusion Models

- Using **GPU** cluster for parallel training large diffusion models on MS COCO dataset using SHELL scripts.
- Fine tuning of diffusion based object detection to improve the accuracy and generalization on satellite images.
- Acheived **mAP** of 0.89 (higher the better, between 0 and 1) for the object detection on satellite images (detection of cars, houses, trees from satellite images).

#### **PROJECTS**

#### • Content-based Game Recommendation System

- Implemented **data preprocessing** and cleaning techniques on a diverse dataset of 10,000+ games, ensuring high-quality input for the recommendation engine.
- Developed advanced text vectorization methods to **extract meaningful features** from game descriptions, improving recommendation accuracy by 25%.
- Created an **interactive Streamlit dashboard** with dynamic visualizations, allowing users to explore game similarities and recommendations.

## • Legal Chatbot on Canadian Constitution using Llama 2

- Designed and implemented a **data pipeline to ingest, clean, and structure** constitutional data, ensuring up-to-date and accurate information for the chatbot.
- Legal Chatbot using Llama 2, processing and analyzing over 500 pages of Canadian constitutional documents with 95% accuracy in legal interpretation.
- Developed a user-friendly interface using Streamlit, resulting to increase user engagement and reducing legal research time for non-experts.

### • End-to-End ETL pipeline using Azure Databricks and PySpark

- Used sales and transaction data to create end-to-end pipeline for ingesting, transforming and loading the data.
- Applying business logic on data for the transformation layer to load data into PowerBI.
- Technologies used: Azure Databricks, PySpark, AWS.

#### RESEARCH PUBLICATIONS

- Mohammad Jasim Usmani and Krzysztof Skonieczny, "Accelerating Graph Networks for Real Time Physics Simulation", 6th European-African Regional Conference of the ISTVS, Lublin, Poland, October 2023, 2023.
- Mohammad Jasim Usmani and Ahteshamul Haque, "Power Management of Solar PV Systems for PEER Load," IEEE Transactions on Industry Applications, Volume: 57, Issue: 6, 2021. Impact Factor: 4.4
- Mohammad Jasim Usmani and Ahteshamul Haque, "Power Management of Solar PV Systems for PEER Load," International conference on Power Electronics, Smart Grid and Renewable Energy, Kerala, India, 2020.
- Mohammad Jasim Usmani, Ahteshamul Haque, V S Bharath Kurukuru, Mohammed Ali Khan "Power Management for Hybrid Energy Storage System in Electric Vehicles," *International Conference on Power Electronics, Control and Automation, New-Delhi, India, 2020.*